Actually, I’ve been wanting to talk about this for a few days now.
然后其实前几天我就一直想讲一讲
About how to lay low and wait for better times.
关于这个怎么样蛰伏起来
How to navigate through your life when things aren’t going so well.
就是怎么样在自己的人生
When the luck in your life isn’t on your side.
命运的运气不是那么好的时候呢
Don’t struggle against fate.
啊不要与命运做抗争
Just go home and read some books, right?
就是回家读读书啊对吧
Play some games,
玩玩游戏呀
Ancient people would play the zither,
古人就是弹弹琴啊
Compose some poems,
做做诗啊
Go fishing, and such.
钓钓鱼啊之类的
I'll open the door for my kitten,
我给我小猫开门啊
Wait a moment, go out.
稍等出去吧
Go out.
出去吧
Luna
露娜
Well, when I was young, I wasn't particularly a believer in fate.
哎其实我年轻的时候呢不是特别的相信命运啊
I always thought that our destiny is in our own hands.
我总认为命运掌握在自己的手中
I still believe that destiny is in our own hands.
我现在也认为命运掌握在自己手中啊
However, when it comes to certain events in life, I feel that most of the time, when doing things, if you want to strive for excellence, strive for success, it’s not an easy task. It takes a bit of serendipity It needs to be the right moment
但是呢一些时间上的一些事情上来讲 我觉得很多的时候来讲 做事情 如果说你要追求卓越啊 追求成功啊 这不是一件容易的事情 需要机缘巧合 需要在机缘巧合的时候
And you did the right thing at the right time
你又在正确的时间做了正确的事啊
Clearly, it’s not the right time now
现在看来明显不是正确的时间啊
For example, when I went to the comic convention
比如说我这次去漫展啊
I had a small speech for about 30 minutes
也就有一个啊30分钟的一个小讲话啊
I have a brief talk every day
每天有一个小讲话
And I basically talked about
然后我其实就给大家讲了
The strategies for starting a media account
讲这个自媒体的起号策略啊
How do you go about creating a channel or something like that?
怎么样做号啊什么的之类的
Then someone reported me.
然后就有人给我举报了啊
Just because I said one thing.
就因为我说了一句话
What I said was actually a fair statement.
我说其实是一句公道话啊
Let me repeat this for you.
我跟你们再重复一次
What did I say?
我说了什么
Then you tell me if it’s fair or not.
然后你们看看这句话公道不公道
I said I started college in 03.
我说我03年上大学
Right?
对不对
Back then, after I came out, it was 358 thousand
那个时候我出来以后就是358千
And I thought, finding jobs for college graduates nowadays is so tough
而我寻思现在的大学生工作这么不好找
It's also 358 thousand
也是358千
Housing prices have gone up over the past 20 years, right?
20年房价都上涨了对吧
But salaries haven't risen
但是工资没有上涨
I feel that the young people today have it really hard
我觉得现在的孩子太苦了
So I said this much
我就说了这么一句话哈
Actually, if you look at it
其实你看啊
I've done so many live streams Hundreds of live streams Thousands of videos I still only have three videos to this day Those are the same three videos from my Weibo days There was an issue
我做了这么多场直播 几百场直播啊 上千个视频 我到现在也只有三个视频 还是我在微博时代的那三个视频啊 啊有问题
So I took the initiative to remove and delist them
然后我自己主动给删除下架了
I’ve never had any trouble with the review process
其他的从来没有说说为难过审核
Or been taken down due to complaints or anything like that
或者说被人投诉下架之类的没有
So it shows that I’ve never really had any extreme views
所以说明我一直就没有什么过激观点之类的啊
He's just speaking the truth
说的都是一些大实话
But let me tell you, Brother Rong
但是荣哥跟你说呢
I was chatting in the group the other day
就是那天我在群聊里边聊
We were discussing who understands what an unsuccessful life looks like
就是说谁更了解一个不成功的人生是什么样啊
Because I'm not a successful example
因为我不是一个成功的一个范例啊
A truly successful example should be like Lei Jun
一个真正成功的范例是应该像雷军那样啊
Pang Donglai is a very inspiring and
胖东来那样那样来讲是一个非常励志的
highly successful one
非常成功的一个啊
an example from the intelligentsia
一个是知识分子啊
A top student
学霸
one is a businessman who came from the grassroots
一个是草根出来的商人啊
they are very conscientious
像他们是非常有良心的
and in comparison
而且相对起来
especially this Xiaomi now
特别是现在这个小米
Su Qi used to be so impressive
这个苏七之前还牛逼哄哄的
but now there's another issue
现在又出事了
there's a problem with public relations again
公关上又有问题了
so I increasingly feel that Lei Jun is actually a pretty good person Such a responsible person. A couple of days ago, a Xiaomi fan scolded me. I wonder how I would feel if I said something like that these days. Because whatever I say, it evokes some feeling. I'm not basing this on current events.
所以我越来越觉得雷军其实是个不错的人 很负责任的人啊 前两天米粉骂我 这两天不知道我这么说会有什么感觉 因为我说任何感觉 我不是说不是说根据现在的时事啊
This comes from...
这个来的
Rather, it comes from my own personal feelings.
而是根据自己的自身的感觉来的
Speaking of not being successful,
说到不成功
Actually, I can offer more insights to everyone.
其实我倒是可以给大家提供更多的经验
You see,
因为你看啊
I actually started back in 2002,
其实我从2002年的时候
when classes were divided into science and arts streams.
那时候分文理班
I should have been placed in the arts stream back then.
我那时候就应该分到文科班啊
Sometimes in my dreams, I find myself back in high school,
我现在做梦有时候经常是回到高中
re-taking the college entrance exam.
又重新参加一次高考
This shows that,
说明在我心里来讲
it's something I deeply regret.
这是一个我觉得非常可惜的一件事情
After all these years of education,
读了那么多年书啊
In the end, I got into a second-tier university.
最后考了个二本
Computer science wasn't even my favorite major.
计算机也不是自己喜欢的专业
Right?
对不对啊
And art wasn't really mentioned either.
艺术也没有说
I started right away.
刚开始就上
But then I took a big detour.
后来折返了一大圈啊
I went to Europe.
去了欧洲
Then I headed to the United States.
又去了美国那边
That's where I finally learned what I wanted to learn.
才把要学的东西都学了
Spent a fortune
花了一大堆钱
Wasted a lot of time
花了一大堆时间啊
Youth has slipped away
青春也过去了
Until one is in their late thirties
直到三十七八啊
This person finally succeeds
这人才成功
Right?
对不对
But this isn't success by worldly standards
这也不是世俗意义上的成功啊
We can't say we've reached the pinnacle Isn't it? But in the end, that's how it is. Looking back at the past 20 years, We finally have a chance to catch our breath. At least we can take a breather now. Well, how to put it,
也不能说一下咱就到了天了 不是 但是呢总归这么来 就是从过去的20年来看啊 总算喘口气了啊 总是能喘口气了 嗯怎么说呢
You were confused at the time, being in the midst of it all.
就是你在那个时候在这个当当事者迷
Sometimes, like me back then,
有的时候你像我那时候
I initially thought my major wasn't good enough.
最开始就是觉得我学的专业不好
I wanted to go out and study it again.
我想出去把专业再读一遍啊
I want to switch to a different major.
我想换个专业读
It feels quite simple.
很朴素的感觉
But since I'm going to France,
但是呢我由于去的是法国
I have to relearn French.
又得重新把法语要学会了
I'm already in my mid-twenties.
啊啊啊已经二十四五了
Starting to learn French,
开始学法语啊
Then I went to Canada and had to take the IELTS.
后来去了加拿大又得考雅思
By that time, I was 26.
那时候都啊26期了
I had to take the IELTS.
要考雅思啊
It's just really tough, you know.
觉得觉得就是很辛苦啊
Everyone else goes out to study for a master's degree.
别人出去都是读研究生啊
I've gone out four times, and all for bachelor's degrees.
我出去读了他妈的读了四次都是本科啊
So, this is the situation.
所以这个东西就啊
But I won’t do it unless it’s something I like.
但是我呢不干自己喜欢的专业呢
I can’t feel settled until I finish studying what I love.
不把自己喜欢的专业学完了呢
I wouldn’t feel at ease.
我自己就不踏实啊
Others study one major.
别人都是学了一个专业
And then they dislike it.
不喜欢了
People often switch majors for postgraduate studies
人就考研换个专业啊
or they just muddle through their jobs
或者人家就呃凑合干
and just do the work directly
这活就直接就干了
I, on the other hand, am quite a believer in the power of education when it comes to academic qualifications especially foreign degrees I have a very high regard for them but to be honest, at that time the family unfortunately lacked the financial means Most of the time, it was my relatives who helped me a lot.
我呢还是特别迷信学历的一个人啊 对这个学历啊 洋文凭啊 这东西呢非常的看好 但是说实在的那个时候来讲 家庭呢只可惜财力不足啊 很多的时候来讲更多的是这个啊我的亲族啊
Uncle helped me a great deal.
啊帮伯帮助我了很多啊
At that time, my parents didn't have much money.
父母其实那个时候来讲并没有那么多的钱
Often times,
好多的时候来讲
As everyone knows,
大家也知道
I didn't do much serious studying when I was in school.
我读书的时候也没有干什么多少正经事啊
I tried all sorts of ways to make money.
去用各种方法挣钱呀
I was short of money.
缺钱
Sometimes, it can be quite painful in your daily life.
其实有的时候呢它是一件让你生活上比较痛苦
But in terms of ability,
但是从能力上来讲的话
it will inspire some of your capabilities,
他会激发你一些能力
so I made a bit of money,
所以也发了点小财
earned a little cash,
赚了点小钱啊
though I wouldn't call it a small fortune,
也不能说是小财了啊
but I ended up losing it all again,
至于最后又被我败出去了
that's just my bad luck,
这是我自己的倒霉的地方啊
after learning so much,
这是学了这个这个这个这个学了这么多学
the fortune teller told me,
然后给我算命的人跟我说
You’re destined for a life of hard work from a young age.
你就是少年劳碌命啊
Whether it’s palm reading,
无论是看手相
or looking at facial features,
看长相啊
or checking the Zi Wei Dou Shu and the Eight Characters of Birth,
看这个紫微斗数生辰八字啊
or even using Tarot cards and other tools,
还是塔罗牌东西的东西用了一遍啊
and even Nordic rune stones were used, the calculations, all led to the same result, so we call this cross-referencing. From multiple sources and perspectives It's like asking an AI Don't just ask DeepSick
然后北欧服石都用了 算 算出来的结果都是一样啊 所以来讲咱们这叫cross reference啊 多个渠道多个地方来讲 咱就跟问AI似的啊 别光问deep sick
Ask Douban as well
豆瓣也问一问
Ask KIMI too, right
KIMI也问一问对吧
Ask iFLYTEK as well
科大讯飞也问一问
Ask ChatGPT too
鼠标g p ChatGPT也问一问
What’s it called, that thing from Musk
唉马斯克那叫什么来着
I won’t mention that one
他那我就不提了啊
That big fool Musk
这马斯克那大傻瓜
Anyway
然后就是无论怎么样
It's a hard life from a young age
就是少年劳碌命
You'll spend all the money you earn when you're young
就是你年轻的时候挣多少钱都会赔出去
And I will keep making you suffer
然后我会一直吃苦压制你
But you'll feel that during that period
但是你会感觉到就是在那段时间里边儿
Some of my
我的一些啊
For example, the feeling of suffering and being mistreated
比如说啊受罪受虐的感觉
Gradually turned into me
后来慢慢的变成了我
Empathy is part of this imaginative ability.
同理心跟这个想象能力的一部分
He will also gradually internalize some things.
他也会逐渐的内化一些东西啊
Of course, if we can avoid suffering,
当然来讲的话就是能不吃苦的话
we should try not to endure it.
还是尽量不要吃苦
But hardship also has its power.
但是苦难它也是有力量的
As long as you face it head-on,
只要你正视它
it has the power to shape you.
它就有力量
And I don’t want to say anything
然后我也不想说什么
that sounds cliché.
就是陈词滥调的啊
Encourage everyone to do their best This thing is not interesting But I want to tell you all It's this bitter thing, you know When averaged over each day It's just boring It's just not pleasant
鼓励大家怎么怎么样 这东西没有意思 但是我就跟大家说 就是这个苦这个东西吧 它平均到每一天来讲 它就是无聊啊 他就是不爽
But it's not something you should dwell on every day
但不至于你天天要是想着他呢
It's just uncomfortable
他也就难受
If you think about it
如果你想啊
This is how it works
这东西是这样
If I had started thinking about it 20 years ago
如果我在我20年前啊
I would have pondered
我就开始琢磨啊
Oh, it turns out I only got lucky at 37
哦原来我到37岁才转运
Then I would have skipped all those years
那我这多年就我就跳过去吧
Then your life would have just skipped over
那你人生就一下就跳过去了
Actually, during this time
其实在这当中来讲
Your so-called success would have been about making money
你所谓的成功也就是钱赚到了啊
Back when you weren't making money
那之前来讲没赚到钱的时候
your life wasn't a waste, you know
其实你的人生啊也不白给
and when you finally start earning
而且你到了后来那一步你赚到钱了
it's all connected to every day before
其实跟以前的每一天都有关系啊
can you say that the years of your hard work were for nothing?
你能不能说你这几年吃的饭都没有用吗
they've become part of your bones and muscles
他已经变成了你的骨头跟肌肉啊
that's how it often goes
很多的时候就是这样
so I recommend that everyone
所以我建议大家
if you've been sending out hundreds of resumes now
如果你现在啊投了几百个简历
Can't find a job
找不到工作
Or you're currently in a job you dislike
或者说呃你现在干了一个不喜欢的工作
Or no matter what your current situation is Or you're recovering from an illness As long as your basic living needs are met You won't suddenly starve Or run out of money immediately Such as ending up on the streets
或者你现在无论是怎么样啊 或者说现在生了病再恢复身体 只要你生活上没有啊 突如其来的会饿死 或者说会马上没钱 就流落街头的这种痛苦以外啊
You must be able to hold on
啊你一定是要撑得住
Try to take good care of yourself
就是尽量把自己的身体照顾好
And
然后呢
No matter what
无论怎么样呢
Don't overthink it
不要去想太多的
Don't worry about the uncertain future
有的没的未来怎么样啊
Or what the distant future holds
遥远的未来会怎样啊
What the world will be like in the future
将来世界会怎样
What will become of me
我会怎样
Don't dwell on it
不要去想啊
Make the most of today.
把今天过好了
We have plenty of food and water today.
今天的啊食物饮水充足啊
The air is fresh.
空气新鲜
Look at how much sunshine there is.
你看阳光充足啊
Just get a good night’s sleep.
睡个好觉就行了
When it comes to many things,
很多事情来讲
it’s about not rushing.
就是你着急
Your mood swings,
你的情绪变化呢
in the grand scheme of things, don’t really matter.
对这个世界的大环境来讲呢是没有用
And you must believe this one thing
而且你一定要相信一点
no matter what happens
就是无论怎么样
if we look back at the past decade or so now
现在我们再回看过去的十几年的历史啊
we actually feel that those days were pretty good for everyone
反而觉得其实那过去的日子大伙都挺好的
it's tough now
现在比较难
but back then, it was tough too
但是其实你在当时来讲的话
it was still really hard back then you never think the present is easy because you can't compare it to anything else When compared in the long run you might feel it’s different but we also say, regarding all these things
当时那个现在仍然很难啊 你永远不会觉得现在有多简单 因为你没有办法跟任何东西做比较 比较了 以后来讲的话 你可能感觉是不一样的 但是我们也说所有的这些东西来讲
are they really that important?
真的很重要吗
these things aren’t actually important
这些东西其实并不重要啊
these things aren’t really significant
这些东西其实并不重要
what truly matters is how you feel inside
真正重要的是你内心的感受
do you feel that things are good now?'
你是不是觉得现在是不错的啊
Let's look at Japan's so-called lost 30 years
我们看日本的所谓的失去的30年啊
The 30 years following the bubble economy
泡沫经济之后的30年
In many cases, it's also about industries
很多的时候来讲也是行业啊
Some industries have become less profitable
有些行业不太好赚钱了
Some industries can rise and fall
有些行业可以有上升下降
No matter what
无论怎么样
You need to have a basic confidence in yourself
你要相信自己有一个基础的自信
Regardless of how the world changes, rises, or falls
就是无论是世界上升下沉变成什么样
Whether it's war or peace
战乱还是和平
I can survive
我都能生存下去
I will have a spark of life left
我都会有一息尚存
I will surely fight my way through
我一定能奋斗出来
Think about the Three Kingdoms period
那你想三国时代
the Three Kingdoms, the Jin Dynasties, and the Southern and Northern Dynasties
三国两晋南北朝
the end of the Eastern Han Dynasty
东汉末年
all the way until the Three Kingdoms were unified under the Jin
一直到啊三国归晋啊
how many years of chaos it was
那混乱了多少年
right?
对不对
But does that mean we stop living our lives?
但人家的日子就不过了吗
Do we stop having children?
孩子不生了吗
Do we stop eating?
饭不吃了吗
No, of course not.
不是的
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
no matter what challenges we face in the future,
无论我们将来问到什么样的艰难险阻
there's one principle you must follow: that is, everyone has a unique purpose and value. Never lose sight of your lofty aspirations. Often, we don't have that much wisdom. We can't see through everything. We can't predict the future. We can't solve all our current problems.
你一定要遵循一条 就是天生我材必有用啊 不坠青云之志 很多的时候来讲 我们并没有那么大的智慧 能够看穿一切啊 能够预知未来啊
No one can do that.
能够解决一切当下的困难
Generally speaking,
不会有这种人的
many people say we must be able to do it ourselves,
通常来讲
but how confident are we really?
很多人说我们自己一定怎么可以
How confident are you really feeling inside?
这自己心里边到底有几分信心呢
We need to pay attention to this as well.
这也要看啊
So, when it comes to major issues, the country has got us covered.
所以很多事情大的事情有国家撑着啊
No need to worry.
不用担心
We have the most elite professionals.
有最精英
The smartest and the best are on our side.
有最聪明的最优秀的啊
We have the top performers from military competitions supporting us.
那些人撑着有全军比武第一
We have the academic geniuses backing us up.
撑着有学霸撑着
Don’t worry, the sky won’t fall.
别担心天塌不下来
Even if it did, the tall ones would hold it up.
天塌下来也有高个儿顶着
Speaking of you
作为你来讲
As for me
作为我来讲啊
We just need to make sure we have a good day every day
我们顺是把每一天过得好
Living in peace, happiness, and joy is all we need
平安幸福喜乐就行了
Like when I go out of town
就像我我一出去外地
Now all I want is to come back and see my dad
现在就想回来看我爸
My mom seeing my child
我妈看见我孩子
I feel really secure
我就觉得很踏实
When I was in my twenties compared to now in my thirties
20多岁的时候跟30多岁
It's completely different from what I thought when I was in my forties.
跟40多岁的想法完全都不一样啊
It's totally different.
完全都不一样
When I was young, I was eager to prove myself.
年轻的时候着急着急证明自己
But give it a try.
可是你试试
Later on, you look around.
后来你看四处
When you try to prove yourself, you end up failing to do so. After you've spent a long time accumulating experience in something, you naturally achieve it. It happened so quickly Often, it's because you have too much self-consciousness
你想去证明自己的时候 反而证明不了自己 等你在一件事情的积累做的时间长了以后 反而你自然一下啊 一下就起来了 好多的时候就是因为你自我意识过剩啊
You're being too arrogant
自己太自以为是了啊
Thinking this is the right path
自以为这样是正确的路
So as you go, you feel less and less confident
所以你走的时候越走越不踏实
You keep looking back
越走越往后看啊
You should be looking forward
越往越往前看
Sometimes, you start to lose faith in yourself
有的时候呢越来越自己呢也没有信心了
And then you become disheartened
然后就垂心丧气了啊
Actually, to be honest
其实事实上来呢来讲的话
the changes in the world don't depend on your material possessions
世界的变化呢不以你的物质啊
or your individual will
不以你的这个个体的意志为转移
In many cases
很多的时候来讲
nature follows its own course
天有自己的天道
So in this context
所以这个时候来讲
I believe the most effective way to change ourselves
我觉得最能够改变我们自己呢
is not to go around sharing our current insights
也不是四处去这个去发表自己的现在的感悟啊
The most important thing is
最主要来讲
I think that now, the more challenging times we face,
我觉得现在就是越是现在
are even more difficult than the present moment.
这时候甚至是比现在更困难的时候来讲
I believe our only wisdom is to focus on reading books thoroughly.
我觉得我们唯一的智慧就是把书好好读了啊
It's not because I'm about to release a new book,
也不是因为我要发新书
and I'm telling you to read now. But rather, books offer a state of flow, a state of calm. Opening a book, I recommend reading physical books. That's right. Because with e-books, you're always using a smartphone,
我现在告诉你要读书啊 而是书它是一种提供一种心流状态 一种平静的状态啊 翻开一本书啊 我要推荐用看纸书 就是这样 因为电子书你始终报的是一个手机啊
or a tablet.
或者pad
So, you're not really breaking free from electronic devices.
你等于还是没有戒断这个电子产品的
This dependency issue,
这个依存证啊
or using a computer which consumes a lot of power,
或者你开着电脑看还费那么多电
but with a paper book, it can accompany you anywhere,
而纸质书呢他可以陪你找到啊
in any space in the world,
人世中间的任何空间都可以啊
it can even join you in a café.
他可以陪你进咖啡馆
I'll accompany you to the park
陪你进公园啊
I'll go with you to the airport
陪你进这个飞机场
Indeed, when it comes to all these things
是的所有的这些事情来讲
The more chaotic things get
就是你越是乱的时候
The more restless people become
越是人心浮躁的时候
You need to maintain absolute inner peace
你要保持内心的一种绝对平静啊
Success is actually a state of mind
成功其实本身是一种心境
It's a state of mind that comes after putting in the effort
是一种经过努力之后啊
A well-adjusted state of mind
的一种调整好的一种心境
So, no matter what
所以无论如何的话
grasping yourself means grasping your future
其实把握好你自己就把握好了未来啊
no matter how many years it might be
无论将来要多少年以后
your destiny will change
你的命运才会有转化
don't worry
不用担心
it could be as long as
长则啊
a couple of decades
20几年啊
or just a few years
短则几年啊
or even next week
甚至下个礼拜可能有转化
So, in many cases, if you were 35 years old, and at 36, you couldn't see this, you might have given up on yourself back then, and you might have missed out on the real outcome, the true main quest and its storyline,
所以很多的时候来讲的话 你如果我35岁 36岁的时候看不到这种东西 当时就放弃了自己 那可能就没有后边的真实结局 跟真实的主线任务攻略的剧情能够看到啊
So what can we do?
所以就怎么着呢
How does that saying go?
那句话怎么说呢
Patience brings clarity, like clouds parting to reveal the moon.
守得云开见月明啊
Sometimes it's like that quote from The Count of Monte Cristo.
有的时候就是像基督山伯爵里那句话似的哈
More of life's achievements
人生的更多的东西
are made in waiting and hoping.
都是在等待与希望当中做成的
The less hope there is in a crowd,
越是人群当中没有希望的感觉
the more despair there is,
一片哀鸿的时候
the better it is for you to rise up.
那正是你崛起的好时候
The less confidence others have,
越是别人没有信心的时候
the more you should gather your own confidence.
其实越是你应该收拢信心的时候
The more others act rashly and blindly.
别人越是盲目的毛躁的在操作一些事情
When the market is in panic,
市场性发生恐慌的时候
this is actually the time you should really focus on reading.
其实这时应该确确实实应该你读书啊
The National Library isn't far away,
国家图书馆也不远啊
you can ride an electric scooter,
骑着一个电瓶车啊
it's just a 10-minute ride,
骑个10分钟
or a 20-minute trip to the National Library to read some books,
20分钟去国家图书馆读读书啊
or play the guitar,
啊抚抚琴啊
or enjoy some PS5 games,
玩玩PS5啊
or play on the Xbox.
玩玩XBOX
Play with your Switch a bit
玩玩自己的switch啊
I was thinking about selling my PICO today
像我今天还想把PICO卖了
I think PICO has brought me a lot of joy Scroll through your phone It's okay to take it easy The big moments in life will come You're not just waiting for things to happen
我觉得PICO其实给我带来的快乐很多啊 刷刷手机啊 躺平一点儿没事儿没事儿 人生的大运会来的 你不是守株待兔啊
Don't be so anxious every day
不要天天那么焦虑
Being anxious all the time won't solve anything
天天焦虑也解决不了任何问题啊
Let your heart out
把自己的心放出来啊
Knowing that the great fortune in your destiny will surely come
知道自己命运中的大运一定会来
To wait for that day
为了等到那一天
To prove that you are not an NPC
为了见证自己不是一个NPC
It will definitely happen on that day
等到那一天一定可以的
Originally, I wanted you to see me in my twenties
原来让你看我20多岁
When I accomplished nothing significant
整个都没有做成什么大事事
Right?
对不对啊
Now, in my thirties
30多岁来讲
It's been the last two or three years, almost 40.
最后两三年都快40了啊
I'm 37 and a half now.
最后37岁半了
38, 39.
3839啊
Just the last two and a half years.
最后两年两年半的时间
Only in the last 25% of the time did I really start to push myself.
一坤年啊啊最后的25%才努力
Just a little bit.
那么一小下子
The so-called effort was just posting a few more videos.
所谓的努力只不过就多更了几期视频而已
I didn't do much else.
还做了什么其他的事也没有说
I went out to run a marathon.
出去跑马拉松去
Right?
对不对
It's not just anything.
也不是什么
Today, we're talking about someone who ranks first in the entire military, not at this level.
今天要说一个全军比武第一也不是这种水平的
It's not like being the top physics student in the whole province either.
是不是也不是什么全省的物理状元
That's not the case.
那也不是这样的
So, a lot of the time, it's about moving at your own pace. No need to worry too much. I've lived for quite some time now, And I've seen a lot. It's okay You live longer You can see further It's all good There are certain things you just have to follow the natural laws of development
所以很多的时候就是按照自己的步速来 不用太担心啊 我其实活了这么长 能看这么长啊 没有关系 你们活的更长 能看得更长 没有关系的 有些东西就是你要遵循事物发展的客观规律啊
Because you're just one person in it
因为你只是其中的一个人啊
But the tide turns
但是风水轮流转
Thirty years
30年
Thirty years on one side, thirty years on the other
河东30年河西
You must, must believe in it
一定一定要相信一定啊
Every man is born with a purpose
天生我材必有用
There will be a time in your life when you will rise to prominence
这一生一定有你非黄腾达的时候
It's bound to be so
一定是这样啊
There are times when things are simple for him
他有属于简单的时候
Some things make you yield
有些东西他让你折服一下
It's to enhance your abilities
这是为了增加你的能力啊
Sharpening the axe doesn't delay the woodcutting
磨刀不误砍柴工
No matter what you're playing now
无论你现在玩的是什么
Romance of the Three Kingdoms
三国群侠传
Taking Zhao Yun to find all sorts of beauties
拿着赵云去找各种各样的美女
Or when you played Taiko no Nazo
还是你当初玩太阁立志传啊
Traveling all over the world
跑到全世界各地啊
Earning money all over the country
全国各地也来挣钱
Buying low and selling high
倒买倒卖
You need to know that all these inspirational games
你要知道就是所有这些励志类的游戏
Will have a period where you need to hone your skills
你都会有一段时间要磨练自己的能力
Sharpen your abilities
磨练自己的技能啊
Travel and explore
游山玩水
Unlock different chapters of this world
开启这个世界的不同的副本
Take a tour of this world
去逛一逛这个世界
Now is the best time for you to explore this world As long as you can survive As long as lying flat still brings in a bit of money Don't be too anxious About finding a job Of course Let's be honest If you really have a problem of not being able to eat
现在是你逛这个世界的最佳时机啊 只要你还活得下去 只要躺平还能有一点点钱啊 不要太着急啊 找工作的问题啊 当然了 讲咱们说实在的 你真有饿不死的问题
If it really comes to that
真到那个程度来讲
There's also the minimum living allowance
也有低保呢
If you really can't manage
你实在不行
Begging can also help you survive, right?
你乞讨也是可以活下去的对吧
I can survive as an internet beggar with no problem
你像我当个网络乞丐活下去没问题的
Living on a few thousand dollars a month is no issue
一个月几千块钱的活下去没问题
It's just not a dignified way to live
只是活的不体面啊
You might not have a car
可能没有车
No house
没有房子
Can't get married right away
没有能马上娶老婆
Others might think your life is a failure
就让别人就觉得你可能人生很失败
But look at me
那你看看我对吧
Divorced in middle age
大年离异啊
With a child and a cat
有娃爱猫
Isn't that all there is to being a man?
男人不也就这样嘛
People will label you
人家演出会给你贴标签
It doesn't matter
没关系
As long as you live a contented life
自己过得踏实就行
The key is to find peace in your own heart
自己关键是要在自己内心里让自己心安
As long as you're at peace with yourself
只要自己心安啊
This world will be a happy place for you
这个世界对你来讲他就是幸福的